Guide to the South African Poster Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
South African poster collection
1969-2009
1969-1994
MS 1574
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
35.75
(14 boxes)
The collection consists of over three hundred posters and related oversized material which document the government and politics of South Africa, primarily from the era of apartheid to the first democratic elections open to all races in 1994. Many of the posters represent numerous political parties, organizations against apartheid, and voter education groups. The cultural life of the country is represented by materials pertaining to South African poets and artists.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; South Africa Collection, MS 1559; South African Apartheid Collection, MS 1500. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The posters are arranged alphabetically by organization name. A small section of poster-like materials, such as calendars, maps, newspapers, and photographs, are arranged by category, and alphabetically by organization or personal name within each category. Additions to the collection are arranged in a similar pattern.
Scope and Contents
The South African Poster Collection consists of posters and other oversized materials which document the political, social, and cultural life of South Africa, primarily from circa 1969 through 1994. The posters are arranged alphabetically by organization name. Additional oversized materials are arranged by category, and then alphabetically by organization name, personal name, or title within each category. Additions to the collection are arranged in a similar pattern.
Additional materials on South Africa are available in the following collections:
AFRICA COLLECTION, Manuscript group 605
AFRICAN POSTCARD COLLECTION, Manuscript group 1575
SOUTH AFRICA COLLECTION, Manuscript group 1559
SOUTH AFRICAN APARTHEID COLLECTION, Manuscript group 1500
SOUTH AFRICAN HISTORICAL COLLECTION, Manuscript group 1556
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Apartheid -- South Africa; Elections -- South Africa; Voting -- South Africa; Posters -- South Africa
- Inventory
  - Posters
    - Africa Fund [12 different posters on apartheid], [1980?] (Folder 1A)
    - Africa Muslim Party (AMP) [2 different posters], undated (Folder 1A)
    - African Christian Democratic party (ACDP) [1 election campaign poster], undated (Folder 1A)
    - African National Congress (ANC) (Folder 1A)
      General note
      See also: Inventory Box 7
      - ANC: 1912-1982 (South African Youth in Struggle), undated (Folder 1A)
      - Advance to National Democracy! [3 posters with different slogans marking 1990 as "The year of Peoples' Action for a Democratic South Africa"] (Folder 1A)
      - The authorized Madiba Collection [poster with pictures of silk and textile memorabilia for Nelson Mandela], undated (Folder 1A)
      - "After years of struggle.. now is the time for freedom!" [4 posters with different election campaign slogans], [1993?] (Folder 1B)
      - 47th ANC National Conference: Peoples Power for a Democratic Future, 1991 July (Folder 1B)
      - Christmas and Eid greetings cards [by ANC offering its goodwill and best wishes to South Africa and its peoples], undated (Folder 1B)
      - "Food for all: ANC demands lower food prices, no VAT on basics, drought relief for all", undated (Folder 1B)
      - The Freedom Charter [6 different posters], undated (Folder 1B)
      - "From Anti-apartheid to Pro-democracy" [3 posters with photos of Mandela and slogans supporting his presidential candidacy], [1993?] (Folder 1B)
      - Happy Birthday! [signatures of several people wishing Nelson Mandela a happy and joyous 75th Birthday], undated (Folder 1B)
      - "I have got my ID.., get yours and vote for freedom!" [5 different posters calling voters to register], [1993?] (Folder 1B)
      - Mayibuye (Journal of the African National Congress) [8 posters advertising various issues of the journal, 1991-1994], undated (Folder 1B)
      - Nelson Mandela for President: vote for Peace, Freedom and Democracy! [4 different posters in support of Mandela's candidacy for president], undated (Folder 1B)
      - Now is the time to... be informed, choose your representatives.. [29 different posters with quotes of ANC's political and economic agendas and names of 200 candidates for the National Assembly], [1993?] (Folder 1B)
      - NP Rule= Disaster [6 posters with different messages and slogans opposing the National Party (NP) and its candidates], undated (Folder 1B)
      - Solidarity with ANC! [2 different posters] (Folder 1B)
      - Stop Savimbi's war! Recognise elected Angolan Government! [issued by ANC], undated (Folder 1B)
      - Tribute to Heros
        - Chris Hani, 1942-1993 [13 posters with different public messages and slogans published in commemoration of the assassination of Chris Hani (general-secretary of the South African Communist Party and member of the National Executive Committee of ANC) on April 10, 1993], [1994?] (Folder 1B)
        - Oliver Reginald Tambo, president of ANC, 1969-1991 [8 different posters], undated (Folder 1B)
        - We salute our leaders [3 posters with photos of ANC founders and heroes], undated (Folder 1B)
      - We Demand... [7 differ posters with slogans demanding peace, freedom, democracy, interim government, constituent assembly], undated (Folder 1B)
      - Working together for jobs, peace and freedom [9 posters with different slogans conveying ANC's promise for "A better life for all"], [1993?] (Folder 1B)
      - 1984 Year of the Women [10 posters with different slogans and messages on Women and ANC in the struggle against apartheid], undated (Folder 1B)
      - 1993: Year of Democratic Election [4 [posters with different slogans in support of ANC] (Folder 1B)
    - Anti-Apartheid Movement [London and other countries]
      - Anti-apartheid calendar '88, [1988?] (Folder 1C)
      - Anti-apartheid slogans and messages [25 different posters published by trade unions and other anti-apartheid groups], undated (Folder 1C)
      - Isolate Apartheid, Sanctions Against South Africa [4 posters with different slogans calling for arms embargo and sanctions], undated (Folder 1C)
    - Concerned Nurses of South Africa [4 posters announcing founding conference, different slogans], 1993, February 12-14 (Folder 1C)
    - Conservative Party (CP/KP) [3 posters with different campaign slogans and candidate photo], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Convention for a Democratic South Africa (CODESA), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Party/Demokratiese Party (DP) [10 vinyl posters with different election campaign slogans and candidate photos], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Apartheid posters (Folder 3A)
    - Federal Party (FP), undated (Folder 3D)
    - Freedom Front/Vryheidsfront (VF-FF) [a slogan with photo of General Constand Viljoen], undated (Folder 3D)
    - Independent Electoral Commission (IEC) [15 different voter education posters], undated (Folder 3D)
    - International Defense and Aid Fund (IDAF)
      - Nelson Mandela: The Struggle is My Life, [1978?] (Folder 3B)
      - Children Under Apartheid, [1979?] (Folder 3B)
      - Women Under Apartheid, [1979?] (Folder 3B)
      - Zimbabwe in Struggle, 1978 (Folder 3B)
    - The Keep It Straight and Simple Party (KISS), undated (Folder 3B)
    - Mandela, Nelson [artist's sketch of Mandela while in prison], undated (Folder 3C)
    - National Land Committee [calendar with awareness messages on the objectives and missions of the Committee], 2001 (Folder 3E)
    - National Organization of Labour Students and the ANC Youth, undated (Folder 3E)
    - National Party/Nasionale Party (NP)
      - Anti-communist and anti-ANC slogans [15 different campaign posters], undated (Folder 3E)
      - Election campaign slogans in support of its presidential candidate F. W. de Klerk, undated (Folder 3E)
      - The future is at your feet (NP Youth), undated (Folder 3E)
    - National Union of Mine Workers [2 different posters with photos of Cyril Ramaphosa and Nelson Mandela, celebrating mineworkers' struggle], undated (Folder 3E)
    - New Republic Party (NRP) [bumper stickers and 5 different election posters with photos of party's candidates], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Nigerian National Committee Against Apartheid [3 different posters calling for sanctions against the apartheid regime of South Africa], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Pan Africanist Congress of Azania (PAC)
      - The 25th Anniversary of the launching of the Decisive Positive Action Campaign Against Pass Laws which resulted in the Sharpeville and Langa Shootings on the 21st March 1960, 1985 March 21 (Folder 3E)
      - The 80's -Decade of the Azanian Revolution, undated (Folder 3E)
      - Support the Pan-Africanist Congress of Azania (PAC), undated (Folder 3E)
      - Vote PAC [2 different posters], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Progressive Federal Party (PFP) [10 different election posters with slogans and photos of party's candidates], undated (Folder 3E)
    - South African Communist Party (SACP) [poster issued on the occasion of the 70thanniversary of SACP, 1921-1991] (Folder 3E)
    - South African Congress of Trade Unions (SACTU), undated (Folder 3E)
    - Sports Organization for Collective Contributions and Equal Rights (SOCCER), undated (Folder 3E)
    - Truth and Reconciliation Commission [two different posters announcing activities of the Commission and encouraging people to make their statements by contacting the Commission at th nearest office], [1994?] (Folder 3E)
    - Women's National Coalition (WNC) [8 different posters on women's rights issues], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Workers International to Rebuild the 4thInternational [Socialist Movement]
      - Announcement for a public speech to be held in Natal, 1994 April 13 (Folder 3E)
      - Announcement for a public speech to be held in Salt River, 1994 March 5 (Folder 3E)
      - Vote Workers International for a Revolutionary Workers Party, No Compromise Socialism Now [election campaign slogan], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Workers' List Party (WLP) [2 posters with different election campaign slogans], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Ximoko Progressive Party (XPP) [election campaign poster], undated (Folder 3E)
    - Unidentified photos and posters, undated (Folder 3E)
  - Calendars
    - American Committee on Africa. Published by the Committee in cooperation with the United Nations Centre Against Apartheid [each month contains a poster by a different artist on the theme of apartheid; text in English, French, Portuguese and Arabic], 1978, 1979 (Folder 4A)
    - "Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU): ten fighting years, 1985-1995", 1996 (Folder 4A)
    - "The Full Colour 1990 Picture Calendar," by Caroline Cullinan [A Weekly Mail Publication] (Folder 4A)
    - "Liberation Calendar" [published by O.A.U. Liberation Committee], 1993 (Folder 4A)
    - Rioters Digest. Michaelis [School of Art] Society. Cape Town, Deersur Press. [calendar for the months Jun to Sep with daily news entries on the subject of apartheid; 5 leaves], 1976 (Folder 4A)
    - "...Salutes Our Heroes: Mandela, Tambo, Luthuli, Dadoo, Fischer, Sisulu," [Snapper Clothes], undated (Folder 4A)
  - Maps
    - Final consolidation proposals for Kwazulu [by Bantu Administration and Development, Development Work Division], 1973 March 4 (Folder 4B)
    - Proposed magisterial district boundaries for Kwazulu [by Bantu Administration and Development, Development Work Division], 1972 January 8 (Folder 4B)
  - Newspapers and news clippings
    - New Nation [cover page of the Mandela Release Commemorative Issue], 1990 February (Folder 4C)
    - Share: Looking at Life in South Africa, 1990 Mar, May (Folder 4C)
    - Sunday Times [cover page reads "Election Results Drama"], 1994 May 1 (Folder 4C)
    - Volkstem [United Party], 1974 October (Folder 4C)
  - Photographs/reproductions
    - Blair, James, photographer [large mounted photograph of two native women], 1977 (Folder 4C)
    - Gordon, Robert Jacob [Plettenberg Bay reproduction], undated
      See: Inventory Box 6
    - Kruger, Stephanus Johannes Paulus (1825-1904), undated
      - Boekenhoutfontein [colored reproduction of painting by Sahriel de Jonh? of the homestead of State President Paul Kruger near Rustenburg], 1969 (Folder 4C)
      - 1899, Pretoria [reproduction of 1901 etching by F. Wichgraf of State President Paul Kruger and his executive council], undated (Folder 4C)
    - Langenhoven, Cornelis Jakob [nine broadsides reproducing a collection of photographs presented by the Cape Provincial Library Service in celebration of his centenary, 1873-1973; captions in Afrikaans] (Folder 4C)
    - Sacks, Shelley ["Images from South Africa," portfolio of six signed prints], undated (Folder 4C)
    - South African poets [thirty broadsides with photographs and biographical sketches; in Afrikaans], 1977 (Folder 4C)
    - Thompson, Clarence C.
      - "Hold the Day" [in honor of Nelson Mandela] (Folder 4C)
      - "Pathway to Freedom" [in commemoration of the United Nations International Year of Sanctions against Apartheid] (Folder 4C)
    - African National Congress (Box 5)
      - A Better Life for All [poster of Nelson Mandela, 21.5 ft. X 3 ft.], [1994?] (Box 5)
    - Gordon, Robert Jacob
      - 1778 Panoramic View of Plettenberg Bay [color reproduction consisting of two sections, each measuring 4.5 ft. X 1.5 ft.], [1994?] (Box 6)
    - National Party [vinyl] wall hanging of party logo, 4 ft. x 10 ft.], [1994] (Box 7)
- Additonal Material, Circa 2003-2006, undated; Accession 2007-M-007
  - African National Congress
    - Mbeki for President, undated (Box 1)
    - "They fought for freedom", undated (Box 1)
  - Cape Town Month of Photography, 2005 February 16- March 20 (Box 1)
  - Department of Arts and Culture (Box 1)
    - Library Week [2 copies], 2005 March (Box 1)
    - Library Week, 2006 March (Box 1)
  - "Drawing Room" [art exhibit], undated (Box 1)
  - Helen Suzman: Fighter for Human Rights [exhibition], 2005 March (Box 1)
  - Out in Africa: Gay and Lesbian Film Festival, 2005 March-April (Box 1)
  - Project Vote, undated (Box 1)
  - Publishers book promotion posters
    - Book covers, Circa 2005
      - Ahmed Kathrada Memoirs (Box 2)
      - Beyond the Apartheid Workplace: Studies in transition (Box 2)
      - The Dassie and the Hunter: A South African Meeting (Box 2)
      - The Dream in the Next Body (Box 2)
      - The Elusive Moth (Box 2)
      - Flowers of the Nation (Box 2)
      - GHAAP: Sonnets from the Northern Cape (Box 2)
      - Homecoming: Voorkamer Stories (II) (Box 2)
      - Life Sentence: A Biography of Herman Charles Bosman (Box 2)
      - Rough Gide to South Africa: Lesotho and Swaziland (Box 2)
      - This Carting Life (Box 2)
      - This Life (Box 2)
      - Within Loving Memory of the Century: An Autobiography, Azaria J. C. Mbatha (Box 2)
    - Booksellers' Choice Awards, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Bosman, Herman Charles [books by], undated (Box 3)
    - Brink, Andre, undated (Box 3)
    - Chimurenga: Who No Know Go Know, undated (Box 3)
    - Cameron, Edwin, undated (Box 3)
    - Literary Awards, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Marais, Eugene N. [books by], undated (Box 3)
    - Umuzi [books printed by], undated (Box 3)
  - Women in Government Gender Advocacy Programme [2 posters], 2003, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Workers International Vanguard League, undated (Box 3)
- Additional Material, Circa 2005, 2007; Accession 2013-M-037
  - Poster advertising DRUM, a South African magazine, Circa 2005 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    One side has an image of Nelson Mandela; the other side an image of Thandiswa Mazwai, a South African musician, singer, and songwriter.
  - "Making Peace Exhibition 2007: Two Presidents, Two Fighters, Two Peace Prize Winners" (Box 1)
    Poster has images of Nelson Mandela and Albert Luthuli, former presidents of the African National Congress and recipients of the Nobel Peace Prize. Making Peace, an exhibit of photographs and text, was launched at the Nelson Mandela Foundation, 2007.
- Additional Material, 2008-2009; Accession 2014-M-023; 6; (3 boxes)
  There are 32 posters from various groups documenting the 2009 elections, many in both English and Afrikaans. There are also five exhibition poster from the District Six Museum.
  - Election posters, 2009 (Box 1, Box 3, Folder 2)
  - District Six Museum exhibition posters, 2008 (Box 3)